all right um
the two questions i i want you to discuss in the
group and turn in jeweler the results right to ta
one of the question is about as a government
agency i said this national defense
departments so when we think about defense
national defense is something related to military
right it should be very complex so think about
it it's a complex system right complex system so
it is not a tiny one it is a big one
complex one and it should be very reliable
all right it has a bad line and it's a little
take it long right so then you can take out
some methodology that's not suitable you're not
going to use prototyping of course all right
so you should think about reliable you have longer
no time allowed to finish that so the best answer
should be water for water all right so you
better use waterfall because it's national or a
governmental agency they need the documents right
so use water for if your answer is apparel then
you you have enough staff to to group them and
then they conduct a sub sub project all right okay
so then you gotta address that well this project
is very very complex and they need the documents
and you have the deadline and the requirements
should be very stable right because they are
not going to to change that often so you're going
to use a structure methodology right it could be
waterfall and you said that's
all well we have an experience
project manager and they know or he or she knows
how to subdivide it that's the group into you know
this is a project right that can
shorten shortens the development spirits
then you you use apparel and so fine this and the
second question is about an executive ceo ryan
wants to have an innovative
innovative function that can help
drill down or have a quick summary
of the company all right quick summary
or drill down with a graphical
display all right so that function
it should be very new and fancy
all right so the best question would be
extreme programming all right because
in you might always the secretary of ceo
often write about the hint or get some
some requirement or needs of the ceo
and you just do it that that's right
and probably would change very often right
because even the ceo just has several notion about
the effects
to show right and you are
the member of the design team
you should propose and conduct the design
right in a quick way and changes often
right and meets the requirements of the
ceo in a very short time so the best
methodology will be extreme programming you
might say that i wanted to use scrum well scrum
could be right yeah that's the secondary choice
right because one you have a formal team right um
and you will yeah probably you can use the
scrums so scrum is more formal you have lots of
product made out and you have a fixed
schedule right it's a burn down chart because
you're going to finish that in a very very short
time to do the events like the activity right so
you can you can use scrum right
but school the team is bigger
than extreme programming so like ceos then
you actually you need to use scrum all right
but you wanted to use it that's the second
choice the best way would be extreme programming
okay so that's the two questions i want to
see the answer like that yeah okay it's alex
yes um i would like to ask a question where do we
draw the line between the project when we call it
this is um a long project and which one we
call this is a short project like where do
we divide the line is it like six months three
months a year two years ten years like that
okay it's pretty good okay good um question
so what do you think about it says um i wanted to
have this function in half an
year you think it's long or short
that's i would say it's a long project
i think it's such a long project
so well actually six months is quite short
right so yeah it is a question we don't have
a definite um or uh precise answer it's a good
good question well it's basic no basically you
want it if it is a project have any year right
six months we regard as a short right or a lot
of things like um we wanted to watch video right
i'll give you a video um well you got to watch
that's what what do you think about if i said
that's uh it's 30 minutes is it short or wrong
um well it depends on what kind of video if it's
documentary then it's short if it's like a movie
then it is short but if it's like a vlog and it
is long so depends on the video content yeah so
we don't have an exact answer all right so if
there's a government then usually this longer
take longer it's a complex it takes longer right
if that is a smaller company one year profits loan
okay so when i say that's on government
agency um you will not expect as a three
months or six months but this is
probably two years right two years
but there's a two year budget to do that
right um so yeah it's a good question
when i said that's um well it's a company
that's there that needs um a very innovative
design then it thinks that i cannot
wait for very long like a year to see
the results so it could be short right so it's
shorter than one year so half an year right yeah
okay any other question good that may
be heavier you raise questions again yes
okay uh well uh i'm going to skip some um
let's gonna jump to the unified process
today's lesson line of the day
today's uh instruction basically is an
extension of last week right because that is
and comes right introductions of the methodology
are not the same but they have something in
common all right there's something in common
the vegetable is something in common and part of
that is a different expression right so this one
unified process you can see that in both textbook
the tennis unified process is a unified process
but you can you cannot see this in
the methodology right so how come
it's unified process a methodology
both of the book says well probably not we
focus on process a unified process so labels
do not categorize it as one of the methodology
rights for any kind unified process or we
call as up in short up right you pee in short
it was proposed by a company
called rational right rational
so r u p unified
so originally
we call this rap because this company was
required acquired booked by ibm then ibm adopts
this and become up right so ibm implements their
project by using unified process a lot right
ibm is an international company we know it
right this very big company and they have
very big projects and very much complex all
right what do you use unified process right so
when we introduce different kinds of methodology i
said that if you are familiar with the methodology
you know how to combine stuff you are not
going to use just one methodology only
all right so you're going to combine
stats in this process unified process
because they use many kinds of methodology
inside that's right if you have documentation
right unified process but it is not a traditional
one okay and this process or this matter right
will produce different version all right
different version they have production right
different version and the the difference between
traditional methodology because you can see that
well um it has a supporting
activity a workflow so we can see
engineering workflow and support right it's a
supporting engineering and supporting workflow
so it's specified that well we're
not going um to only model something
at some time and then go to the next one not
that traditional methodology so we can see
somehow it's quite similar to you know
we start right planning is it inception
initialization similar inception training
when i use a different term elaboration do it
in detail and more so inception here it comes up
always y and here we have what and also have how
all right so when we see that it's it's not
like no like traditional workflow inception
we have the why why do we need to do that and we
also think about the supporting earthquake team
and we conducted so by using that because we have
a very complex system so you are not going to use
up right to to design a very tiny project no it
should be very complex so think about ibm they
help you understand that ibm is an international
company yeah many branches different wallets
and different world has its distinct culture
right so their system gotta be different all
right to suit the needs of different country
all right so make it shorter like seven eleven
right seven eleven is not just one
right one store that many branch
right chance to order a lot of store okay
so they should have a central processing
and also they need to take care of the transformer
right distributed management right so they need
to keep the data and then also you know well
allow
the chain store has its different needs all
right so it make it complex so like that
then you wanted to design a
system that complex situation
so a group of professional comes from
different areas need to talk about a lot
of things because it's a very big all
right and we might test some function
all right based on different needs so you're going
to see that you have idea and couple functions
based on the priority right we
might do some parts and test it
only my deploy means
implements in some chosen store
right so you can see the inception a little
bit so you can see the shaded shaded area
shaded smaller dash
in different phases right so inception
not just business modeling or requirements
some analysis design testing the
model s so for each phase model s
of the workflow including the
supporting supporting workflow all right
and if you see each phase we can
subdivide it partition it right
as iteration what is it different from traditional
one because iteration is not going to go back
let's go forward all right and do this stats and
then go forwards it will finish that as the first
version and come to the others and you're going to
see for example elaboration is a more requirements
let's come clear and more functions yeah
dance they're going to focus on so actually
no there's a lot of methodology
in this matter all right
oh you know it's concordance this is a
process right so this is unified alphabets
together and we also can see extension extensions
of the unified process right so extended modified
versions extension that because you're going to
see we have production whoops let me see which one
what's good
fish
this is same as uh previous one but
extension you're going to see the production
right production it's a release of the
the product line and the supporting ones
you're going to see that well you
have operation cell operation like
the contents of guinness chapter
ones on the new edition it adds
focus on operation right so you can see step
up dv op dev opposite that's the operation
in support and infrastructure management
all right so all the supporting referral
it does not have the um the budgets right
but all that well you can see that's on
that's included in the project management
so yeah configuration change management
change management is about version control
so change that it's a version one when we
when the change from the digits right so from
one to two there's a big change if there's one
third one one the two that that there's smaller
change right so that is the change management
it's about the version control so here you
can see setup iteration and incremental
right so incrementally from inception
a couple iteration each iteration
has the added value or increments function right
and go forwards until ends of production so
production that is the the result the end
product so no inception evaporation until okay
but for the supporting after after releasing
the the production then we still need to provide
a service right there a year or a maintenance
as a production we can see that so that is the
extension of unified process rather combines
two two books together it's gonna stats um
it's a longer time
all right
is any question but no
so which methodology to use right so last
time we got down to two questions and now
i want you to practice another two right
another two so it's just a new version
page 3 the new version page
3 do the exercise h and i
in a group
so h is the page 30
suppose you are an analyst right looking for a
small company to develop an accounting system
accounting so you're going
to develop an accounting
system we know that content is quite complex
even there's a smaller company right accounting
right support the salary wages right and
believe personal leave right so here and there
um that's accounting quite complex so would you
use the unified process to develop the system
or would you prefer one of the other approaches
and why so that is the first question right
smaller company needs a very
complex and difficult system
i suppose you are an analyst developing
a new information system to automate
the sales transaction and manage inventory
inventory for each retail store in large
chain the system should be installed at each store
and exchange data with the mainframe computer at
the company's head office which use the unified
process to develop the system or would you prefer
one of the other approaches oh why so these
two questions all right i'm going to give
you a round on because you're going to have
a break or i'm going to give you 25 minutes
right so these two questions if you don't have the
book take a picture here right h and i and
discuss in the group and turn into a result to ta