Right? Um, the two question I-I want you to discuss
the group and turn into order the results.
Right to T-A, one of the question is about, um as a government agency, I said this on national defense, on departments.
So what we think about defense?
National defense is something related to military, right?
It should be very complex. So think about it is a complex system, right?
Complex system. So it is not a tiny one.
It is a big one, complex one.
And it should be very reliable, right?
It has a pretty line. Anything take long, right?
So then you can take up some methodology that's not suitable.
You're not going to use programming course.
All right, so you should think about reliable.
You have longer no time allowed to finish that.
So the best answer should be water.
Water. All right, so you gotta use water for because the national or governmental agency, they need documents, right?
There is water for. If your answer is parallel, then you you have enough staff to to give them, and then they can talk the sub sub project.
All right. Okay, so then usually address that.
Well, this project is very, very complex, and they need documents.
I'm near the deadline. And the requirement should be very stable by because they are not going to to to change that often.
So you're going to use structure methodology.
It could be word for and used.
That's on, well, we haven't experienced pressure manager, and they know or here, she knows how to subdivide it.
This the group into, you know, this project, right?
They can shorten, shorten the development periods, then you use peril.
So fine this. And the 3rd question is about an executive CEO, right?
Wants to have an innovative, innovative function.
They can't help drill down, or have a quick summary up the company, or Chris, summary, would you down with the graphical display on so that function she be very new and fancy.
So the best question would be extreme programming, right?
Because in you matter with the Secretary of CEO, often, all right, about the heat, or get some some requirement, or needs up, S-E-O-N, you just do it the dad, right?
And probably would change very often, right?
Because even the see, you just has super notion about effects to show, right?
And you're the member the design team, you should propose in conduct the design right in a quick way, and changes often, right?
And meet requirements the CEO in a very short time.
So the best methodology will be extreme programming.
You must say that I want to use scrum.
Well, scrum could be try. Yeah, that's the secondary choice, I guess.
One you have a formal
team, right?
Um, and you will, yeah, probably you can use squams, the scrams more formal.
You have lots of program and, um, you have a fix schedule by the bend on chart, because you're going to finish that in a very, very short time to do the events by the activity.
I'm so you can, you can use squam, right?
But school, the team is bigger than it shouldn't programming.
So, like, see yours, then you actually you need to use squam, right?
But you want to use this?
The 2nd choice, the best way will be train programming.
Okay, so just two questions. I want to see the answer like that.
Yeah, it's alex Is question Good.
I would have to ask a question Where do we draw the line between the project, when we call it?
This is a long project, and which one we call This is a short project?
Like, where do we divide the line?
Is it like six months, three months a year to us?
Ten years? Like, okay, it's pretty good.
Look a good. Um, question. So what do you think about it?
Says, um, I want to have this function in half an year.
You think is long or short?
That's all things long future. It is such a own project.
So, uh, well, actually, six months is quite short, right?
So, yeah, it's a question we don't have a definite um or a precise answer.
The good, good question. Well, it's basic, no, basically, you want to embrace a project, have an year by six months.
We regarded the shot, brian or another thing.
They, um, want to watch video?
I'll give you a video. Um, when we got to watch that.
What you what you think about if I said that's on is 20 min is short?
Hello, um. Well, it depends on what kind of video.
If its documentary and is short, if it's like a movie, then it is short.
But if it's like a flaw, then it is wrong.
So depends on the video company.
Yeah, so we don't have an exact All right, so it was the government then usually this longer, take, longer with a complex tax, longer, right?
Is that is a small company, one year, probably soon.
OK, so when I say that on government agency, and you will not expect that three months or six months, but this is probably two year, right?
Two year, but there's a two year budgets to do that, right?
I'm so, yeah, so, good question.
When I said, that's, um, well, the company, then state needs, um, a very innovative design, then you think that I cannot wait for for very long, like a year, to see the results, so it could be short, right?
So shorter than one year. So have an ear, right?
There any other question? Goods that may be heavier.
You raise a question again? Yes.
Well, I'm going to skip some.
Um, what's going to jump to the Unified Process today s lesson why today, today s instruction basically is an extension the last week, because Dennis and comes by
introductions of the methodology. Not the same, but it is something in common.
All right, there's something common. This to book is something in common.
And in part of that is a different expression, right?
So this one unified process. You can see that in both textbook, the tennis infer process is a indified process, but you can you cannot see that in methodology.
All right. So how come is simified process a methodology?
Both of the books said, well, probably not.
It focused on process, a unified process.
So labels do not categorizes one of the methodology rights for any kind unified process.
Or we call this U-P, in short, up R-U-P, in short, it was purpose by a company called Rational, rational.
So R-U-P uniform. So recently, we call this rap because this company, what's the acquired acquire boat by IBM, then IBM adopt this and become All right, so IBM implements their project by using unified process a lot.
IBM is an international company. We know it.
All right. It's very big company, and they have very big projects and very much complex.
All right, what you use inified process?
So when we introduce different kinds of methodology, I said that if you are familiar with the methodology, you know how to combine them, you're not going to use just one methodology only, right?
So you're going to combine that in this process, unified process, because they use many kinds of methodology inside that, right?
If you have documentation, I unified process, but it is not a traditional one.
Gay And this process, all this matter, will produce different version, different version production, right?
Different version. And the difference between traditional methodology, because you you see that well, um, it is supporting activity overflow, so we can see engineering work, role and support.
Why is supporting engineering and supporting what for?
So it's specified that oil will not going to only model something some time, and then go to the next one.
Not traditional methodology. So we can see somehow, the quite similar to now we start right.
Planning is an inception initialization. Similar inception planning will use a different term, evaluation, students in detail and more.
So inception. Here it comes up with wine.
And yet we have what I know, so have how.
All right, so what we said is, it's not like like traditional workforce inception.
We have the right what we need to do that.
And we also think about the supporting
activity, and we conduct it. So by using that,
because we have a very complex system.
So you're not going to use up
right to to design a very tiny project.
No, it should be very complex.
Something about IP And they help you understand that IBM is an international company.
Many branches, right? Different waterlets and different where has its distinct culture.
Right? So their system gotta be different, like to suit the needs of different country, right?
So make shorter, like 7-eleven. Seven is not just one, right?
One story that many branch by chance to wear a lot of store again.
So they should have a central processing.
And also they need to take care of the chance to win, right?
Distributed management. All right, so they need to keep the data, and also, you know, well, allow the chance the way has its different knees.
All right, so it's make it complex, so that that then you want to design a system that that complex situation.
So group of professional comes from different areas need to talk about, but out of thing, because it's a very big All right, I need my test some function.
I am based on difference. Nice.
So you're going to see that you have idea and couple function.
Listen, priority. We might do some part and tests.
We might deploy means on implements in some children s store.
You can see the inception, so you can see the shaded, shaded area.
Shade is modeled as different places by the inception, not just business model in a requirement, some analysis, design, testing, the model us.
So for each phase, model us of the workflow, including the supporting, supporting a work floor.
All right, you see each face, we can subdivide its passionate, right?
As iteration. What is the difference from traditional one?
Because iteration is not going to go back.
Let's go forward. All right, and to this, so that, and then go forward.
You will finish that, the 1st version, and come to the others.
And you're going to see, E.G.
evaporation. The more requirements is come clear, and more functions.
Yeah, dance they're going to focus on.
So actually, no, there's a lot of mystology in this matter.
I or, you know, it's coon cod.
Is it a process, right? So it's unified or alphabets together.
We also can see extension extensions of the unified process, right?
So extend a modified version, extension that because you're going to see here production, what's Let me see which one.
No, it's good. We find it.
This is Semis, our previous one.
But extension. You're going to see this production, right?
Production is the release of the the, the pro line.
And supporting ones is going to see that well.
Keep operation, the operation, like the contents.
Chinese Chapter one on the new additional at focus on operation, right?
So you can see that up db O-P, step up the desk, the operation in support and infrastructure to management er.
It does not have the budget, right, but all that, or you can see that on that's included in the project management.
So configuration, change management, change management.
This about motion control. The changed is a version one.
When we when the change from the digits right there, from one to two is a big change.
If there's one that one want to that the small change, right?
So that is the change management about the birth control.
So here you can see that iteration and incremental, right?
So incrementally, from inception, a couple of iteration, each iteration has the added value, or equipment function, right?
And go forward until and production.
So production, that is the result, the in product.
So no exception need pollution, that added until, okay?
But for the supporting after, after releasing the the production, then we still need to provide service until year, or the maintenance as a production.
We can see that. So that is the extension of unified process, where it combines to two books together.
That's, um, it's around the time, right?
That question. Hello. So which methodology to use?
Right? So, last time we sat down to to question.
And now I want you to practice.
Another two, Another two. So it's a new version history.
The version history do the exercise.
H and I in a group.
The H especially. Suppose you are an analysis right, working for a small company, to develop an accounting system, accounting, so you're going to develop an accounting system.
We know the accounting is quite complex, even this small company.
Right? Accounting. I support salary wages online, and
believe personal leave, right? So er
one of the other approaches, and why?
So that is the 1st question.
I
small company needs a very complex,
a difficult system. I suppose you are an analyst developing a new information system to automates the sales transaction and manage inventory, inventory for each retail store in a large chain.
The system should be installed at each store and exchange data with a mainframe computer at the company s head office, which use the infight process to develop the system, or which you prefer one of the other approaches?
Why? So these two questions I'm going to give you around on, because you're going to have a break, or I'm going to give you 25 min right?
So this two question If you don't have the book, take a picture here, right?
H and I, and discussing the group and turning your result to T-A.